本期Primal Space由ExpressVPN赞助
This episode of Primal Space is supported by ExpressVPN
1996年4月2日 国际巨星辛迪·克劳馥 克劳迪娅·希弗 安德烈·阿加西
On the 2nd of April 1996, global superstars Cindy Crawford, Claudia Schiffer and Andre Agassi
站在伦敦盖特威克机场的跑道上 等待着一架飞机的到来
stood on the runway at Gatwick Airport, waiting for a plane.
但他们不是要飞往国外某地 因为事件的焦点是那架飞机本身
But they weren't there to fly to some exotic destination, the event was the plane itself;
一架全新金属蓝涂装 印有显眼的百事可乐logo的协和客机
a freshly painted, electric blue concorde, emblazoned with the Pepsi logo.
今天我们将回顾90年代最大规模的市场营销事件之一
Today we're going to look at one of the biggest marketing stunts of the 90s
并了解如此普通的涂装是怎样给这款超音速客机带来严重技术问题的
and see how something as simple as a paint job created a serious technical issue for this supersonic airliner.
在90年代中叶 百事可乐决定更换他们的设计
During the mid 90's, Pepsi had decided it was time to change their design.
他们易拉罐上红色元素太多 和其头号对手可口可乐有点撞衫
There was too much red on their cans which clashed with their rivals, Coca Cola.
所以他们重新设计出近乎全蓝的包装
So, they rebranded to a mostly blue can
为此他们需要在全世界进行一次大规模宣传活动
and needed a big campaign to announce this change to the world.
史称“蓝色计划”
And so began 'Project Blue'.
他们和法国航空商量好
They struck a deal with Air France,
允许他们为当时20架协和客机中的一架重新涂装
allowing them to repaint one of the 20 concordes in existence at the time.
实际上他们拿到了当时最新生产的协和客机 注册号F-BTSD
In fact, they got one of the last concordes to be made, Sierra Delta.
该飞机于1978年制造 得益于新的工艺技术
This particular Concorde was built in 1978 and benefitted from new construction techniques
比如钛合金铆钉 让它成为了最轻的协和客机
like the use of titanium rivets, which made it much lighter than other Concordes.
直到今天 F-BTSD也仍拥有最快环球旅行的时间记录
To this day, Sierra Delta holds the record for the fastest circumnavigation of the globe,
耗时31小时27分钟49秒 经停六次加油
taking 31 hours 27 minutes and 49 seconds including 6 stops for fuel.
拿到了最合适的协和客机后 百事可乐为发布会又定好了良辰吉日 开始干活了
With the most capable Concorde at their disposal, Pepsi set a date for their big event and got to work.
全新涂装是在法国航空位于巴黎的机库内秘密喷涂的
The new paint job was carried out in secrecy at an Air France facility in Paris,
花费超过200升颜料 上千人几小时的工作才完成
requiring over 200 litres of paint and thousands of man hours to complete.
当最后一滴颜料晾干 他们马上把飞机用棕色纸包起来
Once the last drop was dry, they quickly wrapped the aircraft in brown paper
以保证营销内容保密
to make sure the stunt was kept secret.
而发布会在伦敦 他们又在晚上跨越了英吉利海峡来到英国
Since the big event was in London, they sped across the English Channel during the night,
在停进伦敦盖特威克机场一个机库之前一直保密得很好
remaining undercover before being escorted straight to a hanger at Gatwick airport.
全球各地的记者都受邀来到机库
Journalists from all over the world had been invited to the hangar,
参加由克劳馥 希弗 阿加西三人主打的新广告
being told that they would see a new ad, featuring Crawford, Schiffer and Agassi.
之后就是90年代能想到的最牛逼的画面了
What followed was the most 90's event imaginable,
绚烂的灯光秀配上骑摩托入场的超模
a futuristic light show with supermodels arriving on motorbikes.
一番渲染之后 蓝色的协和客机被拉进昏暗的机库
After the main ad was introduced, the blue concorde was wheeled into the dark hangar,
在隐约的迷雾和闪光灯中揭开了真面目
through a fog of smoke machines and strobe lights.
这场发布会花了百事可乐大约五百万美元
This event cost Pepsi around 5 million dollars to produce,
成为了当时最昂贵的广告
making it the most expensive ad ever made at the time.
而这不是“蓝色计划”中唯一一个公众营销事件
But this wasn't the only publicity stunt in the Project Blue campaign.
在协和客机公布之前几个月
Just a month after the Concorde unveiling,
百事可乐成为了第一个在太空打商业广告的公司
Pepsi became the first ever company to shoot a commercial in space.
和平号空间站上的俄罗斯宇航员在太空行走时展示了百事新包装的模型
Cosmonauts onboard the Mir space station took a large replica of the new Pepsi can on a space walk.
这个广告又花了百事可乐五百万美元
This ad cost Pepsi another 5 million dollars to produce.
但广告结束后 百事就换设计了 广告中的设计也就石沉大海了
But once the ad was finished, Pepsi had changed the design of the can and the ad was never aired.
我们在之前某期Primal Space中详细介绍过此事与其他充满野心的太空广告
We go into this and other ambitious space adverts in a previous Primal Space video.
协和客机的新涂装公布后 百事可乐就带它进行了一次巡演
After Concorde's new look was unveiled, Pepsi took the plane on a promotional tour,
飞往了欧洲和中东的十个城市
jetting off to 10 different cities across Europe and the Middle East.
然而 这期间遇到了问题
However, there was one major condition.
他们需要飞慢点
They had to reduce the speed.
协和客机的典型巡航速度是2.04马赫
The typical cruising speed for a concorde was Mach 2.04.
但以此速度飞行会产生大量的热量
But flying at this speed generated a huge amount of heat.
部分原因是流经机身表面的空气与之摩擦
This was partly due to the friction of the air passing over the surface of the aircraft.
不是所有气流可以快速离开超音速客机
with supersonic aircraft, not all the air can move out of the way fast enough.
这会让空气被压缩 并在机头产生高温区域
This compresses the air and creates an area of high pressure in front of the nose,
让飞机变热
which heats up the plane.
全速飞行时 机头温度可以达到127摄氏度
At full speed, the nose would get as hot as 127 degrees
燃料箱和机翼可以超过90摄氏度
with the fuselage and the wings exceeding 90 degrees.
这会让飞机以肉眼可见的程度膨胀30毫米
This would cause the aircraft to visibly expand by around 30 mm.
在驾驶舱内 你会发现飞行机师面板和后舱壁的缝隙会变大
Inside the cockpit, you could see this happening and a gap would open up
between the flight engineer's console and the bulkhead.
在一些退役的飞机中 你还会看到里面夹着一个帽子
On some of the retired planes, you can actually see a cap that was placed in the gap
就是在该飞机最后一次飞行时放进去的 冷却后就卡在里面了
on the final flight, becoming trapped, once the metal shrank again.
这种膨胀在所有超音速飞机中都是个问题
This expansion is a problem in all supersonic planes.
最快的飞机 洛克希德的黑鸟SR-71
The fastest jet ever created, the Lockheed SR-71 blackbird,
就是由各自可以膨胀的很多小零件制造的
was built with many small parts that could each expand.
这会导致飞机在跑道上的时候会漏油
This would often cause the aircraft to have fuel leaks whilst sitting on the runway.
协和客机的设计就是要尽可能降低表面的热量
Concorde was designed to limit surface heat as much as possible.
所以使用了特殊的白色颜料 不但有法国特色 还可以比一般的飞机反射更多热量
They used a special white paint that was much more reflective than typical aircraft paint,
allowing it to radiate more heat.
飞机的燃料也在表面散热中起到关键作用
The jet fuel played a key role in absorbing a lot of the surface heat,
从而让飞机保持在正常温度
helping to keep the aircraft at a nominal temperature.
即使有了这些保护 正常飞行时客舱的墙壁摸起来也是暖暖的
Even with all this protection, surfaces inside the cabin became warm to the touch during a normal flight.
所以 对于新的蓝色涂装
So, with the new dark blue colour scheme,
飞行员被告知他们以超过2马赫的速度飞行不得超过20分钟
the pilots were told that they could only pass Mach 2 for a maximum of 20 minutes.
因此他们飞行中多数巡航速度是1.7马赫
Instead, they flew at a cruising speed of Mach 1.7 for most of the flight,
热量问题就会小很多
where the heating was less of an issue.
F-BTSD带着百事可乐涂装飞了两周
Sierra Delta flew with the Pepsi livery for two weeks
之后交还给法国航空正常运营
before returning to its normal service under the traditional Air France design.
在短暂的营销巡演中 它造访10座城市 进行了14次超音速飞行
During its short stint as a flying billboard, it visited 10 cities and completed 14 supersonic flights.
它进行百事可乐涂装的过程大约花费一百万美元
The process of converting the aircraft into Pepsi colors likely set the company back around 1 million dollars
据估计百事可乐为整个“蓝色计划”准备了5亿美元的预算
and it's estimated that Pepsi's budget for the entire Project Blue campaign was over half a billion dollars.
1996年年底 可口可乐利润还是比百事可乐多近50%
By the end of 1996, Coke were making almost 50% more profit than Pepsi.
即使变成超音速 百事也追不上民众可乐口味的潮流
Even going supersonic didn't make them fast enough to catch the world's most popular cola.
百事可乐天下第一！不服来辩！
协和客机在2003年退役时
By the time Concorde ended in 2003,
它也变成了有钱人的奢侈的旅行方式
it was simply a glamorous way for the wealthy to travel
也是商务人士到地球另一边开会的最快的交通工具
and the quickest way for business people to get to their meeting on the other side of the world.
今天 全球的网络如此发达
Nowadays, the world is more connected than ever
在网上开会可能比坐在狭小的客舱以2马赫飞过去开会更安全
and having a business meeting over the internet is probably safer than flying at mach 2 in a tin can.
当你连接公共WiFi时
Whenever you are connected to public WiFi,
黑客很容易窃取你的密码 邮箱和信用卡信息
it's incredibly easy for hackers to steal your passwords, emails and credit card information.
所以如今拥有一个VPN保护隐私数据是如此重要
This is why it's essential nowadays to have a VPN to keep your data private.
ExpressVPN就是最好的VPN服务商 有全球超过90个国家的服务器和最快的速度
ExpressVPN is the number 1 VPN service, with the fastest speeds and servers in over 90 countries.
ExpressVPN还能让你无区域限制访问互联网
ExpressVPN also allows you to use the internet without any restrictions,
从而让你看某些国家不能看的电影 电视节目和YouTube视频
so you can access movies, TV shows and YouTube videos that are blocked in certain countries.
这是我最喜欢ExpressVPN的一点
This is probably my favorite thing about ExpressVPN
在这之前 我经常会遇到在我的国家看不到的视频
since before, I was always coming across videos that were blocked in my country.
有了ExpressVPN 你就能轻松改变访问的国家
With ExpressVPN, you can easily change which country and server you want to connect to,
完全的自由了！
giving you total freedom!
ExpressVPN支持多平台 多应用连接不同服务器 只需几秒
ExpressVPN is available on every device and the app lets you connect to different servers within seconds.
终极的上网安全与自由 ExpressVPN每月不到7美元
For ultimate internet protection and freedom, ExpressVPN costs less than 7 dollars a month,
如果你访问ExpressVPN.com/primalspace 还能得到3个月的免费试用
and if you visit ExpressVPN.com/primalspace, you can get 3 months for free!
感谢观看本期视频 我们下期见
Thank you very much for watching and I'll see you in the next video.